Guide to the Ernest Rice McKinney Papers, 1929-1935, 1942 AIS.1963.04
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Ernest Rice McKinney Papers
1929-1942
1929-1935
ULS Archives & Special Collections
McKinney, Ernest Rice
AIS.1963.04
0.56 Linear Feet (1 box)
Ernest McKinney was an African American journalist who played an integral role as an unemployed organizer for the National Unemployed League. This collection includes personal papers; it should be noted that McKinney sometimes wrote under the pseudonym of David Coolidge.
Biography
Born in Malden, West Virginia, in 1886, McKinney, also known under the pseudonym David Coolidge, was the son of a coal miner. At different points in his life, McKinney endeavored a variety of jobs which included becoming editor of, This Month, a columnist for the Pittsburgh Courier (1932), Executive Secretary of the Unemployed Citizens' League of Allegheny County (1933), a Social Worker, and Assistant to the Director, Kingsley House. In 1916 an oral history conducted at Columbia University resulted in McKinney writing a 116 page book of memoirs published by Harvard University,The Reminiscences of Ernest Rice McKinney. The memoir deals with the development of the National Unemployed League, depression days; organizing steel workers for CIO, membership in the Workers' Socialist Party; upgrading African Americans in industry; Working Men's Welfare Committees; Workers Party of the United States (Trotskyist Group) and its relationship to Communist and Socialist Parties; and McKinney's resignation from Workers Party.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection is comprised of correspondence, newspaper clippings, a scrapbook and articles by McKinney, cartoons, and miscellaneous material ranging from publications to newsletters. Some of McKinney's papers are located at Harvard University and an oral history was conducted at Columbia University.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Hugh Cleland on October 15, 1963.
Previous Citation
Ernest Rice McKinney Papers, 1929-1935, 1942, AIS.1963.04, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
McKinney, Ernest Rice Papers, 1929-1935, 1942, Archives of Industrial Society, University of Pittsburgh Libraries
Social action; Personal papers; African American social workers -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; African American journalists -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Social workers -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Journalists -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Socialists -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- Social conditions; Socialism; Unemployed -- United States; Social workers -- Political activity; Manchester Industrial Center (Pittsburgh, Pa.); McKinney, Ernest Rice; Pennsylvania Unemployed League. Allegheny County Division; Socialist Workers Party; Unemployed Citizens' League of Allegheny County
- Correspondence of the Unemployed Citizen's League of Pittsburgh, March-April 1933 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Newspaper clippings, circa 1936 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Scope and Content Notes
  Includes poetry, editorials, and several "It Is My Opinion" articles by McKinney on a variety of topics including employment, unions, and politics
- Clipbook (unbound), 1932-1933 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Newspaper clippings regarding employment, politics, President Roosevelt, and unions.
- Miscellaneous publications and periodicals, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ernest Rice McKinney, "The Tactics of the Socialist Party in Pittsburgh: A Rejoinder", 1.
  - David Coolidge, Bulletin on the Negro Question, 2.
  - Constitution and Platform of the Unemployed Citizen's League of Allegheny County, 3.
  - "The Unemployed in Action: A Challenge to the Unemployed of Pittsburgh," Bulletin 3 of the Pittsburgh UCL, 4.
  - Preamble to the Constitution of the Unemployed Citizen's League of Allegheny County, March 1935; 5.
  - Untitled open letter/statement/manifesto of David Coolidge, circa 1935; 6.
- The agenda and minutes for the July 30-31, 1934 Convention of the National Unemployed League, circa 1934 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  2 copies
- Miscellaneous publications and periodicals, 1929-1942 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Demonstrate, the Official Organ of the PA Unemployed League, nos. 1-2, October-November 1934; 1.
  - Flier for "Don't Tread On Me," the Second Annual Convention of the National Unemployed League, 1934; 2.
    The convention took place on July 30, 31 and August 1, 1934 in Columbus, Ohio. 2 copies.
  - Information Bulletin: A Service for Unemployed Organizations magazine issues 1-3, 1932-1933; 3.
  - Abolish Segregation, Jim-Crowism, Discrimination, vol. 1, no. 2, November 1942; 4.
  - This Month, vol. 1, no. 2, June 1929; 5.
    Includes Ernest McKinney, "Holy Men of Aframerica."
  - The Letter: Weekly News of the Center, vol 3, no. 6, February 5, 1931; 6.
- Mass Action, vol 1, nos. 1-5, 17, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Cartoons (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Labor Age Cartoons, 1.
      2 copies, original and copy.
    - Various cartoons assembled from unknown sources, 2.
- Two articles by Ernest Rice McKinney, 1929 and 1933 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "Race Solidarity: An Ideal of No Importance," The World Tomorrow, January 1929; 1.
  - "The Negro's Road to Freedom," Labor Age, vol. 21, no. 9, September 1932; 2.
- Sworn statement of Charles Lewis, March 31, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 9)